Is the melon sweet?
瓜甜么
Who's there?
谁呀
Me.
是我
May I have some?
给我吃一块
Looking for me?
找我呢么
Over here.
我在这儿呢
Come. I'll pay for my meal.
过来，我不会白吃你的
There's money buried under that tree.
听着，那棵石榴树下有钱
Dig it up, it's yours.
挖出来用吧
I'll be back.
我还会再来的
The Master is home.
主人回来了
Yunqiao
云樵
Chunqin
春琴
Hurry
快来
I have to tell you...
我跟你说
There really was buried treasure?
哎！真挖着钱啦
That sound
多么熟悉的暮鼓声
I've heard it in my dreams.
一定是在梦见大唐的时候听到过吧
In the 21st year of the emperor's reign,
贞元二十一年，正月癸巳
the Japanese monk Kukai came to Chang'an
倭国法师空海前来长安
for an exorcism.
驱除邪祟
How long has he been like this?
陛下这个样子有多久了
His eyes haven't shut for a week.
七天七夜，睁眼无眠
Please begin.
请施法吧
Scribe Bai-
白左使
Present.
在
Write: "The emperor died of illness."
写，皇帝猝死于风邪
Write
写呀
Master Kukai-
法师
The emperor's death must be kept secret.
皇上殡天是大内极密
Go, and it'll be as if you were never here.
法师跨出这扇门，就当从未入过唐宫
Oh!
哦
Wipe your shoes.
擦擦鞋底
So I'd come to cure the emperor's disease.
没想到宫里召我是为了皇帝的病
But that was no ordinary illness.
可天子却明不是死于风邪
Master Kukai-
空海法师
Scribe Bai
白左使
Why didn't you say anything?
你刚才怎么不说话
The imperial physician said
太医已经说了
he died of illness.
皇帝死于风邪
No illness keeps a man awake for a week.
七日不眠，不可能是风邪所致
I'm the scribe, I must keep exact records.
在下起居郎白乐天，专写天子行止
I can't write anything I'm unsure about.
不知道皇上真正的死因，我下不了笔
How long have you been a scribe?
白左使在宫中多久了
Three years. Why?
三年了，怎么
The emperor's pet cat is black, yes?
内宫豢养的御猫是黑色的吧
In three years, I never saw a pet cat.
我在宫里三年多，从没见宫里养过猫
When I kowtowed I got fur on my hands.
刚才伏地跪拜，手上沾了一缕毛发
True. Only cat fur is this fine and soft.
不错，只有猫毛才会这么又细又软
What are you looking for?
你在找什么
Pawprints?
猫脚印
Not only did a cat enter the palace,
这就是说，有一只猫不但进了宫
it was near the emperor's bed.
还靠近了皇帝的卧榻
A cat was involved with his death?
你的意思是说，皇帝的死跟一只猫有关
What's this?
什么东西
The Emperor is dead. Li Song is next.
皇帝已死，后即李诵
Who's Li Song?
李诵是谁
The prince, the next emperor.
马上就要登基的太子
He'll be back tomorrow.
他明天还会来
Who?
谁呀
The cat.
猫啊
We'll have to buy more fish.
明天叫人多买几条鱼回来
Nothing too big. He only eats the eyes.
鱼不用大，他光吃眼珠子
This was part of the old palace.
这是前朝旧宫
What's that noise?
哪来的动静
Careful.
小心
Huh. Just a cat.
是只猫啊
It's a time of mourning. Stay alert.
宫里大丧，四处留心吧，走吧
C'mon, let's go.
走了走了
Master Kukai
法师
Scribe Bai
白大人
You're right, there's a cat in the palace.
你说的对，宫里确实有猫
You saw it?
你看见了
No. The night patrol told me.
没有，宫里巡夜的人说的
And another strange thing...
还有件怪事
Go on.
接着说
Chen Yunqiao, an imperial guard,
有个叫陈云樵的金吾卫
had a talking cat at his house.
家里也来了猫，竟然会说人话
Where'd you hear that?
这又是听谁说的
His servants were gossiping.
陈家仆人们传出来的
Too bad I'm leaving.
可惜我要走了
It's none of my business now.
这件事已经跟我没关系
And you, will you report it?
倒是你，上奏了吗
It's none of my business, either.
这件事跟我也没什么关系了
I'm finished. I quit!
我不干了，辞官了
I've retired to devote myself to poetry.
我辞官就是为了专心把我的诗写完
I'm a poet.
我是个诗人
I've heard Chang'an is full of poets.
听说长安遍地都是诗人
I'm different.
我不一样
I could have been a high official.
我是两榜进士出身，可以当大官的
I chose not to.
不做而已
But why be a lowly scribe?
那怎么只当了六品起居郎
That's for my poetry too.
也是为了写诗啊
Only a scribe stays in the palace,
只有起居郎才能整天泡在宫里
seeing the emperor's every move.
看得见皇帝的一举一动
Like a eunuch, minus the inconvenience.
除了不用那个，我就是个太监
Your poem is about palace life?
你在写皇家的故事
Yes. No more questions. I'll say no more.
不错，别再问了啊，我只能说这么多
What's the poem called?
诗名叫什么
Song of Everlasting Sorrow
「长恨歌」
So it's a love poem.
噢，爱情诗
I told you, I'm not talking.
跟你说了，别再套我的话
Who's it about?
主人公是谁
The emperor, right?
是皇帝吧
So you needed to understand him.
所以你才想了解他
Enough!
闭嘴
His love had to be a concubine.
皇帝爱上的一定是个妃子
Explain, why you say "had to be"?
那你说说
皇上为什么爱上的一定是个妃子
He didn't pick his empress. Forget servants.
皇帝一般不爱皇后，更不会爱上宫女
Who else is there?
还有谁
Clever!
厉害啊
You're too kind.
别客气
You're right.
你猜的对
It's about the emperor's love for a lady.
「长恨歌」就是皇帝和妃子的爱情故事
Is it finished?
写完了吗
Not yet!
还没有
When it is, history will remember me.
等写完那一天就是我留名青史的日子
But don't tell anyone yet!
跟谁也不许说啊
Was Li Bo the greatest Tang poet?
大唐最厉害的诗人是李白吧
Li Bo lived a long time ago.
李白不过是早生了三十年
He was lucky- it was a golden age.
沾了些开元盛世的仙气
Have you heard of Bai Juyi?
听说过白居易吗
He is the greatest poet of today!
那才是今天的大诗人
Oh? When will you introduce me?
噢，什么时候也引我见见
Bai Juyi is very full of himself.
白居易，他可狂得很
He makes his own rules,
自称是无情无义无法无天
lives for poetry, and sees no one!
只认诗不认人，谁也不见
Kukai, what's up with you?
空海，你是怎么回事
Why rush back to Japan?
怎么这么快就要回国了
Why did you really come here?
你来大唐到底是来干嘛的
To study with Abbot Huiguo at Qinglong Temple
我想做大唐青龙寺惠果大师的弟子
but I couldn't get a foot in the door.
可惜连山门都没能进去
Kukai, it's not just you.
空海，这一点儿都不奇怪
Qinglong is the home of Tantric Buddhism.
青龙寺是大唐密教的祖庙
Huiguo obtained the Tantric secrets abroad.
当家的惠果大师
当年从狮子国取回了密法
Of more than a thousand monks,
座下有上千僧人
he says none are fit to be his disciples!
可他却说，没有一个够得上做他的弟子
Have some melon!
吃瓜喽，吃瓜喽
One melon can't feed everyone.
一只瓜解不了众渴
I'll make some more.
那就多来几只吧
Great!
好，再来几只
Water
水
It's sprouting! It's sprouting!
发芽啦，发芽啦，发芽啦
Sprouting!
发芽啦
See that?
看见没有
Grow!
长大
Bigger!
再大
Bloom!
开花吧
Bravo!
好
See that? Melons!
看到没有？结瓜了
It's an illusion.
是幻术
They're melons! We all can see them.
明明是瓜，大家都看到了
We've all been taken in.
大家都中术了
Bravo!
好
Let's go.
走吧
Gentlemen- some melon?
二位，吃瓜么
I don't have money on me.
没带钱
I sell illusions, not melons.
我卖的不是瓜，是幻术
You saw through it, so no charge.
你没中术，不能收钱
I'm sorry.
失礼了
Old man-
老伯
only one melon was real, right?
架子上的瓜，只有一只是真的吧
Shh...
嘘
Impressive.
你能看穿不简单
Is that a Japanese accent?
听口音，你是倭国人
My name is Kukai.
我叫空海
It's an honor. This melon is a gift.
难得有缘，这只瓜送给你了
Too kind.
不敢当
What's dripping?
什么东西滴滴答答的
He got me after all!
还是中术了
Toss it, quickly!
还不快扔掉
Now it's turned back into a melon.
我扔的时候又变成西瓜了
What a powerful illusion.
好厉害的幻术
Now I might believe in a talking cat.
我现在相信猫说话也可能是真的
What was that guard's name?
那个金吾卫叫什么
Chen Yunqiao.
陈云樵
Hey, Yunqiao, slow down.
云樵，你慢点儿
The girls don't wait for anyone.
可姑娘啊，不等人
Giddyap!
驾
Chen Yunqiao is the one in the middle.
中间那个就是陈云樵
Here!
赏
Girls, where are you going?
上哪去儿啊小娘子
Come with us!
跟我走吧
Don't take my girl tonight!
今儿谁也别跟我抢啊
You're all here.
这人到的够全的
We want our bonus!
都等着你赏呢
Here!
赏
Where are they going?
他们要去哪儿
Huyu House-
胡玉楼
The city's top brothel!
长安第一妓院
Are you still game?
还跟着去吗
Of course I am!
那当然要去看看
Hurry up, girls.
姑娘们，快点
Coming!
来了，来了
Yunqiao! Yunqiao!
云樵，云樵
Pardon me!
失礼了
I'm Yulian.
我叫玉莲
Why haven't we met before?
我怎么没见过你啊
Yulian is new here.
玉莲姐才来的
Sir.
郎君
This flower is crooked.
这花怎么歪了
Let's go.
走
C'mon. You'll be mine tonight.
今晚上就你陪我了
Sister Lixiang...
丽香姐
How weird.
诶 ！ 奇怪
This is the Tang of romance!
这才是大唐风流
Aren't brothels forbidden to monks?
哎，你们倭国僧人上妓院不犯戒啊
You're entering a brothel.
你是上妓院
I'm here for the beautiful music.
我是供奉伎乐天女
Scribe Bai!
白左使
I got your gown back from the pawn shop.
前两天典当的袍子，刚给您拿回来
Excellent.Pawn it again!
好极了，再拿去当一回
Sure!
是
I see you're a regular.
看来白左使是常客
But first time here with a monk!
带个和尚来还是头一回
It's you who looks like a regular!
我看你才像这儿的常客呢
For you!
赏
Reward them! Tips for all!
赏 赏 赏
Beautiful dancing, Yulian.
玉莲，你舞的真好
Drink up.
喝了
Chen Yunqiao.
陈云樵
Who's that?
谁喊我
Me.
是我
Spent all the money? Want more?
钱花完了吗
Want more?
还想不想要
That's the cat!
就这只猫
Yunqiao, your cat's here with your purse!
云樵，你家小猫又给你送钱来了
I've thrown a feast and paid you all
今天来赴宴的，是个人都有赏
but what to offer a mere animal?
一个畜生，我赏什么呢
Have a fish.
赏你条鱼吃吧
I only eat eyeballs.
我只吃眼珠子
You know that.
你也不是不知道
Whose eyes will you give me?
把谁的眼珠子给我
Over there!
在那儿
UP there!
在上面
Beasfl
畜生
Yunqiao.
陈云樵
Debts must be repaid.
欠债总是要还的
Listen up.
听好了
I'll see you at home tomorrow night.
明天晚上我要去你家做客
MY eyes!
我的眼珠
Chunqin!
春琴
What sort of monster did this?
作祟者是何妖物
A cat.
是一只猫
What's the link to the cat in the palace?
胡玉楼的猫和宫里的猫有什么关联吗
They're one and the same.
两处出现的是同一只猫
Oh?
噢
Three heavy pawprints, one light.
两处留下的爪印都是三重一轻
Exactly the same.
一模一样
But what's that mean?
三重一轻，什么意思啊
One of its legs was injured.
意思是这只猫的一条腿受过伤
Look here, Inspector Li.
李少监，请看
You said the emperor
那么法师的意思是
was 'frightened to death'. By this cat?
皇帝的死也是那只猫所为了
I'm sure of it.
确定无疑
Then we wronged you,
这么说是委屈你了
Scribe Bai.
白左使
You didn't resign.
你不是辞官
Fired, resigned, same thing.
辞官，罢官没什么两样
A lowly official still has principles.
六品小官也有官格
All I ask is not to record lies.
我只求下笔没有假话
Yesterday, they crowned the prince.
昨日太子登基
Straight away, he became paralyzed.
大典刚刚礼成，就偏瘫了
The emperor is dead. Li Song is next.
皇帝已死，后即李诵
The prophecy has come to pass.
预言实现了
No emperor has had a curse before.
天子遭人施咒，前所未有
Who can lift it?
何人可破
Kukai is from Japan.
空海万里而来
He's a famous exorcist.
在倭国是大大有名的驱邪师
Who better to take on the demon cat?
降服妖猫还有谁比他更合适呢
Why do this to me?
为什么害我
You're an exorcist.
你本来就是驱邪师
You want to get into Qinglong Temple.
再说了，你不是想进青龙寺吗
Now you've good reason to stay!
现在你可以名正言顺留下来了
Right.
嗯
What are you thinking?
你又在想什么
Why did the cat attack Chen Yunqiao?
我在想
为什么妖猫攻击的偏偏是陈云樵
He's head of the Imperial Guards.
陈云樵是金吾卫的统领
What's their role?
金吾卫是什么官职
To protect the emperor.
皇帝的卫队
His family has done this
陈云樵的父亲，爷爷全是金吾卫
for three generations.
三代世袭
Three generations?
The cat said, "Debts will be repaid."
那只猫说了一句，欠债总是要还的
But who incurred this debt?
到底是谁欠了债
What kind Of debt
欠了什么债
sees two emperors fall
才让两位天子连着倒
and their top guard attacked?
金吾卫统领也遭到攻击
The palace?
皇城
Why are we here?
为什么带我到这儿来
You asked whose debt it is.
你不是问我是谁欠的债吗
Whose is it?
是谁
A previous emperor for sure.
一定是和前朝有关
One from the past?
前朝
What's the connection to Chen Yunqiao?
前朝和今天的陈云樵有什么关系
Is the cat really coming back?
那猫真的会来吗
He told me so last night.
他昨天晚上亲口说的
You brought on this disaster.
祸可是你惹的啊
You spent the money.
钱是你花的
Shh...
嘘
Chunqin!
春琴
She's your wife.
她是你的女人
Will you save her?
死到临头，你救不救
Help! Help!
来人吶
Open the door!
开门
Yunqiao,save me!
官人，官人救我，官人
Save me!
官人救我
Chunqin!
春琴
Save me, Yunqiao!
官人，救我
How'd you get here?
你怎么在这儿啊
You weren't going to save me.
你不救我嘛
Who are you?
你到底是谁
Yulian is sick?
玉莲怎么了
She fell into a coma.
玉莲姐昨晚晕倒以后就一直昏迷
No, she was poisoned.
她不是昏迷，她中蛊了
Huh?
啊
Get some raw meat, hurry!
去取一块带血的生肉，快
OK.
是
Such beauty,
这么美的身体
rotting like a dead flower!
怎么一烂跟花儿一样败了
No time for poems. Find a brush and ink.
现在不是作诗的时候，快找笔墨
Let me stay for the night.
丽香，今晚让我在这儿住一宿
Hmph.
哼
What's with all the Buddhist symbols?
为什么写这么多卍字
It's not just a symbol. It's light.
卍字不是字，是光
Look.
你看
Here.
来了
Is it fresh?
是刚割的生肉吗
Yes.
是
Give it to Bai.
交给乐天
Needle.
针
Hold onto her!
牡丹，你抓住玉莲
Catch them.
接住
What are these?
这是什么东西啊
Venom worms!
蛊毒虫
They poison living flesh.
这种虫在人体内会发出剧毒
Only raw meat can draw them out.
要用带血的生肉才能把它引出来
Who did this to her?
是谁给玉莲下的蛊
Someone with a grudge.
心怀怨恨的人
For sure it's Lixiang.
一定是丽香
Yunqiao was her lover.
陈云樵原来是她的相好
She hated her for stealing him!
她恨玉莲姐抢了她的人
Not necessarily.
不一定是丽香
The wine was meant for Yunqiao.
这杯酒本来是给陈云樵的
He unwittingly gave it to Yulian.
陈云樵无意中给了玉莲
Master-
法师
Please... save my wife too!
你行行好，把我们家春琴也救了吧
Huh?
诶
Her robes, clouds; her face, flowers.
云想衣裳，花想容
Careful!
小心
Where are you going?
你去哪里
Chunqin?!
春琴
Shh...
嘘
So who was that?
那刚才那个是
An illusion.
那是幻术
How do you know?
你怎么知道
She cast no shadow.
月光下人没有影子
Only cats walk on rooftops.
只有猫才喜欢在屋脊上行走
What poem was she reciting?
他吟的是什么诗
It's by Li Bo.
那是句李白的诗
It likens beauty to clouds and flowers.
形容美人，衣服如云，面如花
When was it written and where?
诗是什么时候写的，在什么地方写的
Let me take you somewhere.
我带你去个地方
What is this place?
这是什么地方
The imperial library.
天子藏书楼
I think of it as my own.
说是我的也行
Over there.
那边
You lost your job but still come here?
你已经不是起居郎了，还敢进来
Whatever.
管他呢
Push, Kukai!
推，空海
Stop.
停一下
What...
诶
A little bit more.
往前推
OK.
噢
Stop.
停
It was the spring of 755.
天宝十五年春天
Emperor Li
玄宗皇帝李隆基
was celebrating his beloved's birthday.
在花萼相辉楼为贵妃举办生日宴
Who was his beloved?
哪个贵妃
The exotic beauty Lady Yang.
有一半胡人血统的杨玉环
The Tang emperor
当年在玄宗朝
had 3000 women, but eyes only for one.
后宫佳丽三千人，三千宠爱在一身
Emperor Li adored her.
李隆基宠爱杨玉环
He filled a giant pool with wine
他在太液池内注酒七千斤
and the hall With 100,000 flowers.
整个花萼楼外，牡丹种了十万株
Guests came from all over.
万方来朝，宾客如云
He called it the Feast of Supreme Joy!
这场宴会名叫 极乐之宴
Emperor Li ordered Li Bo
席间，玄宗皇帝命诗人李白
to write a poem for Lady Yang.
为贵妃写一首诗
Her robes, clouds; her face, flowers.
云想衣裳花想容
Li Bo guarded his talent,
李白这个人，恃才傲物
writing happily about common folk,
一支笔宁写苍生，不写权贵
but shunning the rich and privileged.
一辈子没有给王公贵族们留下半句好话
This poem was the only exception.
唯有这首诗是例外
He wrote it at the Feast of Supreme Joy.
就在极乐之宴上
His first sight of Lady Yang
他第一次见到了杨玉环
drove him to madness.
见到之后，他就疯了
Madness?
疯了
Only madness
不疯
could inspire such a great poem.
不疯哪里写得出这样的好诗
Li Bo wrote at the emperor's behest.
李白承皇帝命，作清平调
The first line...
起始一句就是
Her robes, clouds; her face, flowers.
云想衣裳花想容
Having seen her face,
见到了贵妃本人
why write only of clouds and flowers?
为什么只写云，写花呢
Good monk-
和尚啊，和尚
hers was a beauty beyond words.
这世间有言语形容不出的美人
It's poetry
不是这神来一笔
as romantic as her beauty and his love.
李白哪里写得出
As romantic as her beauty and his love.
杨玉环的美和李隆基的浪漫
Come!
快过来
All great emperors
所有了不起的帝王
want to grow the realm and inspire awe.
都想开疆辟土，威震四方
Emperor Li was no different.
玄宗也不例外
But that wasn't the real him.
但是在我眼里，这都不是真正的李隆基
Daring to give up imperial glory for love-
只有敢于拿一朝盛世
去换一个能和他比翼齐飞的女人
that was Emperor Li.
那才是李隆基
He loved Lady Yang-
他爱杨玉环
he saw her as the soul of the dynasty.
他知道大唐有了杨玉环，才有了魂
Often in my dreams at night,
多少次的午夜梦回
I live in those glorious times-
我幻想着我活在玄宗的时代
I too am at the feast
我也走进了花萼相辉楼
and lay my eyes on her.
我也看见了她
May I ask
我想请教
how many poems did Li Bo write?
李白一生写过多少诗
He was a legend-
他是诗仙
too many to count.
诗多得数不过来
So Why'd the demon cat pick this one?
那为什么妖猫偏偏要念杨玉环这一首
Who was he reciting for?
他在念给谁听
What do you mean?
你说念给谁听
It was for you.
念给你听
If you, like Li Bo,
如果你的诗和李白一样
are writing about Lady Yang...
也是关于杨玉环的
Your "Song of Everlasting Sorrow"
你的诗长恨歌，写的就是
is about the emperor's love for Lady Yang.
玄宗皇帝和杨玉环的爱情故事
Am I right?
我说得对吗
Quality guaranteed!
如假包换
How much for one?
这瓜怎么卖
Didn't I give you one before?
不是给过你一个了吗
Yes. It was delicious.
吃了，好吃所以才又来
Say what you came to say.
想说什么你就说呗
Your magic. There's one thing I don't get.
关于幻术，我有一事不明白
It's magic, what's there to get?
幻术嘛，有什么不明白的
It's just tricks, right?
不就是假的吗
But a killer cat is no mere trick.
可那妖猫夺人眼睛和性命一点不假
So I'd like your advice.
所以我才来向你请教
What do cats have to do with melons?
这可真奇了，猫和瓜有什么关系
If a melon isn't a melon,
如果瓜不是瓜
then a cat...?
那猫
Isn't a cat!
那猫也不是猫
What is it, then?
不是猫，那是什么
You think melons come from thin air?
你以为瓜能凭空变出来吗
Inside the illusion is reality.
幻术里也有真相
So I must look to the cat itself.
所以，真相还得回到猫身上找
Thank you!
多谢
Yunqiao's house?
还去陈家
Will I end up dead and eyeless too?
我会不会也变成一条
被妖猫吃掉眼珠的死鱼
Not yet.
暂时不会
What's that supposed to mean?
这话又是什么意思
It probably knows about your poem.
妖猫应该知道，你在写长恨歌
That tree wasn't here yesterday!
昨晚门前没有这棵树
Who's that woman?
树下的女人是谁
Isn't it Chunqin?
不是春琴吗
No.
不是
Beware the magic!
当心中术
It wasn't like this last night.
昨天晚上，哪里是这个样子
Hey-
喂
gentlemen, come on up.
两位客人，上来坐吧
Have a seat. There's tea.
坐吧，茶都倒好了
Kukai, I hear tea is popular in Japan too.
空海，你到了大唐也懂茶道
Yes.
嗯
You know his name?
你知道他叫空海
I know you, too, Bai Juyi-
我也认识你呀，白居易
the famous poet of Chang'an!
长安城里赫赫有名的大诗人
Indeed.
不错
The one who makes his own rules.
他就是那个无法无天
无情无义的白居易
Juyi, have you finished your poem?
白居易，你的长恨歌写完了吗
I told you she knew you were writing it.
我说过，他知道你在写长恨歌
In fact, you finished it long ago,
其实你早就写完了
but you're not happy with it,
不过一直都不满意
and it's no wonder
这也难怪
because it's not the real story.
你写的都是假的嘛
And Lady Yang didn't inspire Li Bo's poem.
连李白写给贵妃的诗也是假的
He met her only after he wrote it.
写之前，他根本没见过娘娘
You're saying he faked it?
你竟敢说李白的诗也是假的
If it wasn't sincere...
既然李白的诗是假的
why recite it from the roof?
你为什么要在屋脊上吟诵
Her robes, clouds; her face, flowers.
云想衣裳，花想容
Lady Yang loved that poem.
这首诗贵妃很喜欢
She told Li Bo that herself.
是娘娘亲口告诉李白的
But didn't you say they hadn't met?
你不是说李白没有见到娘娘吗
Oh they met.
见倒是见了
But only after he wrote the poem
不过是等到写完了诗
and threw his brush into the pool of wine.
把皇上赐的笔扔进酒池子以后才见的
How do you know all that?
你怎么知道李白写完扔笔的事
I was there.
我在那儿呀
Where?
在哪儿
At the banquet.
在宴席上
Which banquet?
哪个宴席
The "Feast of Supreme Joy".
极乐之宴
Who are you?
你到底是谁
But first tell us about the injury.
先说说你是怎么受伤的
It's your back paw, right?
是左后爪吧
Yes.
没错
I was Emperor Li's pet cat.
我就是皇上亲养的御猫
We should've grown old together.
皇上本该和我相伴终老
But when the rebellion came,
不想一场战祸
he abandoned me
他竟然抛下我一个人
and fled for his life.
逃命去了
And then?
后来呢
After that,
后来
a cruel man buried me alive.
有人狠心挖了个坑，把我给活埋了
But it wasn't my fate to die. I escaped.
幸亏我命大，从地底下逃了出来
That's why you put a curse on him.
这就是为什么你闯进寝宫对天子施咒
He ordered them to bury me.
下令埋我的是大唐天子
I'm not done with them yet!
我就和大唐，没完没了
What do you have against Yunqiao?
和陈云樵结的又是什么怨
It was his father who buried me alive.
活埋我的就是他爹
That all happened thirty years ago.
你说的这是三十年前的旧事
A cat doesn't live that long.
一只猫不可能活过三十年
While here to take revenge
我到陈家报仇
I ate a poisonous fish
没想到吃了他家有毒的鱼
and died under the bed.
死在了床底下
My soul was trapped in my body
我一点冤魂不散，又没人收尸
and I turned into a demon.
才变成妖猫出来作祟
Why use Chunqin to recite the poem?
你为什么借春琴吟唱李白的诗
Why show us Lady Yang by the tree?
又为什么让我们看见树下的杨玉环
Is there a secret you want to tell us?
你到底有什么秘密想要告诉我们
Did I not share her fate?
我的命，不就和一样吗
Who?
和谁一样
Cat skin?
猫皮
Master Kukai, thank you.
法师，谢谢了
Scribe Bai.
白左使
How dare they play banned music.
他们怎么敢演奏禁曲
Lady Yang loved to dance.
一半儿是胡人血统的杨玉环善舞
Emperor Li wrote the song for her himself.
这是玄宗皇帝亲自为杨玉环作的
霓裳羽衣曲
It was banned after the rebellion.
安史之乱以后就被禁了
Yunqiao!
陈云樵
You brought on this disaster!
都是你这个女人惹的祸
It's your fault!
是你
Stop it!
住手
I want you dead!
我让你死
Kukai! Save Chunqin!
空海，快救春琴
Kukai!
空海
Chunqin!
春琴
Don't bury me.
别埋我
It's cold down there...
地下冷
What?
什么
It wasn't me who killed her!
不是我杀的
Yunqiao?
陈云樵
Reward! Reward!
赏
Reward!
Don't tell me that was all an illusion.
别再告诉我这都是幻术
Yunqiao went mad.
陈云樵疯了
Chunqin is dead.
春琴死了
Did you hear her last words?
乐天，你听见春琴死前说了什么
Don't bury me, it's cold down there.
她说，别埋我，地下冷
The cat said he shared her fate-
我的命运跟她一样
was he talking about Lady Yang?
她，指的就是杨玉环吗
They tried to bury the cat alive.
而妖猫说它是被活埋的
He was trying to tell us
那是不是，妖猫想告诉我们
that Lady Yang was buried alive too.
杨玉环也是被活埋的
Do you realise what you're saying?
你知道你自己在说什么吗
You say don't let the magic fool you
你几次三番提醒我别中术，别中术
but you trust everything that cat says.
到头来妖猫说的每一句话你都相信
This time you fell for it, not me!
这回是你中术了，我可没有
Who said you could come in?
谁让你进来的
The door was open.
门开着
I told you- Juyi doesn't receive guests!
告诉过你了，白居易不见客
What good is that?
撕没有用
The cat saw these drawings
妖猫都看到了
and made Chunqin your vision of Lady Yang.
所以他能把春琴幻化成你想象中的贵妃
From palace to brothel to Yunqiao's house-
从宫里，到胡玉楼，再到陈云樵家
he has been guiding you towards the truth.
妖猫一路都在引你寻找贵妃死亡的真相
But why me?
为什么偏偏是我
Because of your poem.
因为你在写长恨歌
I also understand
我也明白
that if Lady Yang was buried alive
如果贵妃是被活埋的
then your years of toil were wasted.
那你的长恨歌就白写了
Understand?
明白
You just get here and you understand?
你刚走进这间屋子就说你明白
Cold nights agonizing over a single word-
你没尝过我在寒冬的夜里
苦苦写诗跪求一字的折磨
what do you know of "toil"?
就知道什么叫心血
Because you are Juyi.
因为你是白居易
Because thirty years have passed,
因为三十年过去了
and only you keep Lady Yang in your heart.
仍然心系贵妃的只有你
Her death is recorded in history!
杨玉环之死，于史有载
The rebellion, Emperor Li's escape,
「安史之乱」玄宗出逃
and the mutiny of his troops,
路上遇到兵变，玄宗无奈
forced him to order
不得不亲赐白绫
Eunuch Gao to strangle her.
让太监高力士勒死了贵妃
You know
一个起居郎
a scribe can falsify records.
不会不知道史书也有造假的可能
That's why
正因为我知道
I risked my life to steal the evidence.
所以我才冒死闯进了凤栖楼，偷出了物证
Oh?
噢
From the palace? Let's see it!
你从宫里偷东西？给我看看
'Jade Girl' was her baby name.
玉奴二字是杨玉环的乳名
A lock of hair- it was a token of her love.
头发，是她送给李隆基的爱情信物
Emperor Li died years ago,
leaving behind countless treasures.
玄宗过世多年，留下了无数遗物
But his most secret treasure chest
我打开他最私密的七宝函
held only this silk pouch.
里面却只有这只香囊
If he didn't adore her,
要是李隆基不爱杨玉环
why keep a lock of her hair there?
一绺儿头发何必珍藏到今天
You're in love with her too.
你也爱上了她
You're as obsessed as him.
你也为她疯狂
I want justice for her.
我是为她不平
The dynasty's decline wasn't her fault.
大唐陨落不是她的错
She shouldn't be buried alone.
杨玉环不该如此孤独地被埋葬在马嵬驿
So I'll do what Emperor Li could not-
所以我要做一件连李隆基都做不到的事
I'll bring her back to life!
让她再活一回
But as you wrote,
但当你一动笔
you had doubts.
就发现事情不是你想的那样
Aware of this,
妖猫知道你的疑问
the demon cat is trying to tell you
才会用各种方式告诉你
you didn't get the story right.
长恨歌的爱情故事，是假的
Sure, I'll never write as well as Li Bo.
我知道我写不出云想衣裳，花想容
I'm happy to live in his shadow.
我可以一辈子活在李白的阴影里
Just don't say my poem is a lie.
但你不能说我的长恨歌是假的
Speaking of lies,
其实要说起假
I'm a fake myself.
我也是个冒名顶替的假货
You're not a monk?
你不是和尚
I'm an ordinary shaman.
我是说我只是个普通的沙门
Japan's top exorcist is my master.
我师父才是最好的驱邪师
But he is unwell,
他身体病弱
so sent me in his stead.
才让我顶替他来到大唐
I'm here for the Tantric teachings.
来，是为了求法
Kukah
空海
In all my years, I've yet to find enlightenment.
我修了一辈子得不到解脱
I suffer in mind and body.
身心还是很痛苦
China has obtained the Tantric teachings
大唐的 「无上密法」
for release from the cycle of life and death.
是能够超越生死的天法
KukaL
空海
please,
拜托了
you must bring back these teachings.
不管怎么样，你都要入唐把它带回来
And so I resolved to come here.
也许是为了帮我下定入唐的决心吧
Those were his last words.
师父在那一剎那员寂了
Master.
师父
Goodbye.
我去了
The journey tested my pride and confidence.
船入大海，我的骄傲和自信受到了考验
Aren't you afraid?
你不害怕吗
With my baby asleep, I'm at peace.
孩子睡熟了，我就很安心
The waves pushed me under.l was terrified.
我被浪卷进海里，怕得要死
I struggled to stay alive.
拚命挣扎想活下去
In the face of death,
背熟了的咒语经忏
I forgot every prayer.
在死亡面前统统忘光了
But I'll never forget her words.
但我却记得那个母亲对我说的话
Why couldn't I stay as calm as her?
是什么能让她那样的平静
Since I survived,
我既然活下来了
I must seek answers in those teachings.
就一定要在大唐无上密中
找到这个答案
I found a witness to Lady Yang's death.
贵妃死的时候，我有证人在场
Back then, in the palace,
以前在椒房的时候
I was Lady Yang's morning maid.
由我去照顾娘娘的起居
Ask me anything you like.
你们有什么想问的，就问吧
Were you there when she died?
贵妃死的时候嬷嬷在场吗
Yes.
在
The emperor gave the order.
是皇上下的令
I wove the silk execution cloth
我亲手绣的白绫
and gave it to Eunuch Gao.
交给了高力士
See?
没错吧
And then?
之后呢
When they called us in,
叫我们的时候
Lady Yang was already dead.
贵妃已经死了
So you didn't see Gao strangle her.
所以，你并没有亲眼看见高力士勒死贵妃
I couldn't bear it.
谁忍心啊
I'm sorry.
对不起
Even the emperor turned away.
连皇上都回避了
So how did you know she was dead?
那，怎么知道贵妃已经死了呢
Captain Chen of the guards checked.
金吾卫陈玄礼，亲自来验看
He held incense under her nose.
他把一支香放在贵妃鼻子前面
The smoke didn't waver,
香烟不动
proof that she'd stopped breathing.
证明贵妃已经断气了
How did she look after death?
死后的贵妃是什么样子的
Like she was sleeping,
就像是睡着了
even lovelier than when she was alive.
比活着的时候更美
So you wove the execution cloth.
原来是你织的白绫
She looked like she was asleep?
嬷嬷说贵妃死后就像是睡着了
That's strange.
确实很奇怪
If she'd been strangled,
如果是被勒死
she'd be in terrible pain.
为什么脸上没有痛苦的样子
I don't get it either.
我也在想
Who was Captain Chen?
陈玄礼是谁
I told you before.
我告诉过你
Yunqiao is a third-generation guard.
陈家是三代世袭金吾卫
Captain Chen was Yunqiao's dad,
陈玄礼是陈云樵的爹
the instigator of the mutiny.
马嵬驿兵变的主谋
It's clear now-
现在清楚了
the cat attacks anyone involved in her death.
妖猫报复的全是和贵妃死有关的人
So then why spare the old woman?
那为什么这位老宫女活了下来
What!
啊
Hurry!
快
I shouldn't have brought you here.
我就不该带你来见她
Letian
乐天
Who else survived the mutiny at Maweiyi?
我想知道马嵬驿兵变后还有哪些人活着
Catch.
接着
Did any escape?
遗缺待补
Chao Heng? Who's that?
晁衡，是谁
A Japanese, like you.
他也是你们倭国人
A senior envoy. He was here a long time.
遣唐使留在长安的，属他官职最高
Abe no Nakamaro?
阿部仲麻吕先生
That's the one!
就是他
Oh.
哦
He was at Maweiyi too?
马嵬驿兵变，他也在
Yes, but he died a long time ago.
他在，可是他早就去世了
Because he's Japanese,
加上又是倭国人
he had no records in the archives.
坊间找不到他的文字记载
So I wrote "to be completed".
所以才写了遗缺待补
Did Abe have a home here?
阿部先生在长安有家宅吗
Yes, his widow Bai Ling is still alive.
还有个侍妾活着，名叫白玲
Shhh...
嘘
Hurry!
快
You again.
又是你
And who is this?
还带了谁来
Pardon us.
失礼了
I'm Kukai, a shaman from Japan.
我是日本来的沙门，我叫空海
This way.
请
Did Mr Abe ever wish to return to Japan?
阿部先生当时有没有想过回日本
He changed his mind at the last minute,
阿部先生已经到了码头，又改变了主意
watched his ship sail, and returned.
看着船走远了
Then returned to Chang' an.
又返回了长安
Why?
为什么
Because of a woman.
为了一个女人
He didn't know if she was alive or dead.
因为不知道对方的生死所以留下了
Did he ever find out?
先生后来知道那女人的生死了么
I never asked.
我没有问他
He was here a long time.
先生在大唐多年
Did he leave behind a journal?
没有留下什么文字吗
Yes. He asked me to burn it.
先生留下一本日记，让我烧掉
But you couldn't do it?
是先生留下来的，一定舍不得烧吧
No. Regretfully, I read it.
真惭愧，我偷偷读了先生的日记
That's how I knew he loved another.
才知道先生爱的不是我
Yet you stayed. Aren't you lonely?
一个人留在长安，一定很寂寞吧
Why not give me the journal?
把日记交给我吧
Maybe I can release his soul
也许我们能解开先生死前的悬念
and salve his troubled heart.
让先生的心得到安息
Thirty years have passed.
三十年过去了
I still remember the first line-
还记得读过的第一句
I'm a heartless man.
我是一个无情的人
I'm a heartless man,
besotted with the emperor's woman.
但我却疯狂地爱上了皇帝的女人
Today is her birthday.
今天是她的生日
All of Chang'an is astir.
长安城轰动了
To allow them a glimpse of her,
为了让所有的人都能看到她
the emperor came up with this idea.
皇帝竟然想出了这样的主意
Her exotic looks
杨玉环因与常人不同的模样
had won his love.
反而受到皇帝的宠爱
It was an enlightened age,
大唐的开明大度
and she was its pride and joy, its symbol,
以此引来了四野八荒的目光
to which all eyes were drawn.
她是大唐骄傲的象征
I will profess my love to her
我要当面向她说出我对她的爱慕
at her birthday feast tonight.
而且，就在赴宴的今夜
Everyone says,
人人都说
all this is her idea.
这一切都是贵妃的意思
It's her vision
借 「极乐之宴」
of the Tang in all its glory.
挥洒出她心中真正的大唐气象
What a marvelous woman!
她竟然是这样一个奇女子
M'Lady, the emperor wants to know-
娘娘，皇上让我问你
do you like his gift of this red robe?
他送你的这件红色霓裳
Do you like it- or not?
你是喜欢呀，还是不喜欢呀
Where is the emperor?
皇上在哪儿
M'lord, M'lady. Watch this!
陛下，娘娘，请看
A tiger for M'Lord, flowers for M'lady!
虎给皇上，花给娘娘
I still prefer my cat.
我还是喜欢我这猫
The illusionist was Yellow Crane,
变虎的人名叫黄鹤
the realm's most famous magician.
是当今最有名的幻术大师
White Crane.
哎，白龙
Coming!
来喽
I want to catch those flowers!
我要抓住那些花儿
Go
去
How rude!
放肆
No rules tonight!
今晚不算
Catch!
接着
I'd never seen the two boys before.
这是我第一次见到这两位白衣少年
They were Yellow Crane's disciples-
他们是黄鹤的徒弟
Red Crane and White Crane.
一个叫丹龙，一个叫白龙
So there really was a cat?
还真有只猫
You reek of wine,
你这一身的酒气
you don't wash, your robes are filthy.
澡也不洗，衣服也不换
Even dirty, I'm cleaner than you.
我不洗澡不换衣裳，也比你干净
Get off.
去
Li BO,
李白
wealth and rank is yours at last.
你的荣华富贵就要来了
Who are you?
你是谁
What do you want?
有什么事
My name is Gao Lishi.
我是高力士
His Majesty wants you to write a poem.
皇上派我来跟你讨诗
What about?
写什么
A great beauty.
写美人
There aren't any.
没有美人
Sure there are. It's not so hard.
当今谁最美，你就按谁写不就得了
No one tells me what to write.
别人让我写的
Can't do.
不会写
The Emperor isn't 'no one'.
皇上算不算别人呢
If he tells you to write, you write!
他叫你写，你就得写
Take off my boots and I'll do it.
你给我把靴子脱了，我就写
I only do that for the emperor!
我只给皇上脱靴
Lady Yang said
娘娘说
at her birthday feast, all are equal.
极乐之宴无有尊卑上下之分
This is a test. So it's not true after all.
我找个官大的一试，果然就试出是假的了
Gao Lishi-
高力士
Yes.
在
You're disobeying her and the emperor!
你欺负皇上和娘娘啊
It's Lady Yang's hairpin.
这是娘娘的翠翘
No!
去
What are you looking at?
看什么呢
So you're the Flying Cranes?
你们就是白鹤少年
Amazing.
太奇妙了
It's an illusion.
是幻术
It's nothing-
没什么
Just "now you see it now you don't".
一切都是也有也无，真真假假
Am I wrong?
我说的不对吗
No.
对
Give Lady Yang her hairpin.
把翠翘还给娘娘
Keep 'u.
留着吧
Now you see it now you don't.
不一切都是也有也无吗
You're older?
你大
lam.
我大
Dad found him by the river
他是我爹在河边一村子里捡来的
and called him White Dragon.
白龙这个名字都是我爹给他取的
Don't lie to Lady Yang.
你对娘娘不该说谎
My dad was a gambler.
我爹赌钱输了
He sold me to Master Yellow Crane.
把我卖给师父了
The master is my father.
师父就是我爹
Wait.
站着
Look at me.
转过来看着我
I was an orphan
我从小就没有父母
raised by my uncle.
是在叔父家长大的
Living under another's roof
寄人篱下
made me grateful and beholden.
反倒让我对别人的好
Made me grateful and beholden.
一点一滴都想报答
You're the same, yes?
你也一样，对吧
Only as a pair are you the Flying Cranes.
缺了一个，你们就不是白鹤少年了
Her robes, clouds...
云想衣裳
Come.
过来
Her face, flowers
花想容，呗
Spring breezes, a dewy loveliness
春风拂槛露华浓
seen only in heaven's peaks
若非群玉山头见
and moonlight pavilions.
会向瑶台月下逢
Finished!
好了
No revisions?
不改改
Not a word.
一字不改
What did you write?
写的什么呀
Is it good?
写的好不好啊
See for yourself.
自己看
Time for my nap.
我要睡了
（花萼相辉之楼)
Letian
乐天
Li Bo's brush.
李白的笔
The demon cat was right!
妖猫全说对了
Wake up!
快起来，快起来
Lady Yang is here to see you.
娘娘来看你来了
Thank you for my poem.
谢谢你写给我的诗
Huh?
啊
Have I written you a poem?
给娘娘写的诗
Which one's that?
哪一首啊
Her robes, clouds, her face, flowers
云想衣裳，花想容
It's beautiful.
写得真好
You flatter me.
娘娘这么夸，俗了
It's not that great.
没那么好
Anyway, I didn't write it for you.
再说这诗也不是给娘娘写的
Of course you did.
这诗就是给娘娘写的
If not for M'Lady, who was it for?
不是写娘娘，那是写谁啊
I don't know,
我也不知道
but I can't lie.
可我不能骗娘娘吧
Put on your shoes.
把靴子穿上吧
Li Bo.
李白
You enrich our dynasty.
大唐有你，才真的了不起
Her robes, clouds, her face, flowers.
云想衣裳，花想容呗
Why's it written on your back?
怎么写你背上了
Did he write this on his own
这诗是李白自己要给娘娘写的
or did you make him do it?
还是你让他写的
Your Majesty-
皇上
Turn around.
转过去
Speak.
说
It was Li Bo's idea.
是李白他自己要给娘娘写的
Lady Yang loves it.
娘娘是真喜欢啊
Should I reward him?
赏还是不赏
Yes, richly.
重重赏
Have him exiled...
让他明天就离开长安
for life.
永远不许再回来
And your poem?
那皇上写的那首祝寿诗
Should I give it to M'Lady?
要不要也给娘娘送过去看看
No need.
不用了
Abe!
阿部
Why are you here?
你来做什么
To see me, I'm sure.
阿部先生一定是来找我的
We received your gift.
你送的玛瑙，皇帝和我都看过了
Very nice.
好
No-
不
that's not why I'm here.
那不是我想和娘娘说的话
I know why you're here.
我知道你想说什么
But remember-
但是你记住了
at no time
不管什么时候
will you find Lady Yang on her own.
贵妃，永远都不会是一个人
We're bound together for eternity.
我们生生世世，永不分离
Let's go.
走了
The last guests are here.
最后一位客人就要到了
The emperor didn't kill me
皇帝没有杀我
but his compassion and disdain
可他的仁慈和轻蔑
slayed me in front of my beloved.
还是让我倒在了贵妃的面前
He had written something.
他却在一旁写下了四个大字
Abe- the calligraphy is for you.
阿部，字送给你了
Guess what it means.
猜猜什么意思
The Greatest Happiness
极乐之乐
To control all others-
驾驭所有的人
that was his "greatest happiness".
就是帝王的极乐之乐
The last to arrive was General An.
极乐之宴的最后一位客人是安禄山
The emperor welcomed him
皇帝散发击鼓迎接他
with a martial performance.
欢乐被推向了高潮
He knew General An wanted to rebel
安禄山要造反的消息早就传遍天下
but made him feel special.
皇帝仍然以盛宴款待这个要杀他的男人
He was ruler of the world and trusting.
皇帝是宇宙之王 天真赤子
Above the fray.
凌驾于一切之上
This is Yanqiu Gate.
这里就是延秋门
Ten days after the feast,
极乐之宴十日之后
general An rebelled.
安禄山就起兵造反了
At first, Emperor Li stayed put.
李隆基原本不逃
But An wanted Lady Yang
安禄山扬言一定要得到杨玉环
so they fled Chang' an.
这才是他离开长安的唯一理由
100,000 went with him.
结果，十万人由此出逃
I'm still the emperor!
我还是皇帝
During the escape,
安禄山造反的同时
the imperial guards
原本护送皇帝出逃的金吾卫
mutinied at Maweiyi.
在马嵬驿发动了兵变
They said only Lady Yang's death
逼迫皇帝处死杨贵妃
would end the rebellion
打破安禄山得到贵妃的梦想
and bring peace.
平息叛乱
Eunuch Gao has returned.
皇上，高力士回来了
Open the doors.
把门全打开
The head of Lady Yang's brother.
杨国忠的人头
Now Captain Chen wants Lady Yang's head.
陈玄礼，要我再用这个盘子
托着娘娘的人头出去
Impossible!
妄想
Then he can't promise his loyalty.
那陈玄礼，就不能担保金吾卫的忠诚了
Your Majesty...
皇上
What is it?
你想说什么
Try-
你可以试试
But it's unlikely.
可我赌你输
Yellow Crane.
黄鹤
M'Lady- a word in private?
娘娘，我能和你单独说一句话吗
You want to take me to Japan?
你这时候来见我，是要我随你去倭国吧
It's also the emperor's idea.
这也是皇上的意思
The rebels killed your brother.
因为见到娘娘的兄长，姊妹
都被叛军杀了
It's all my fault.
那都是因为我
But if I go, they'll kill the emperor.
要是我走了，下一个杀的就是皇上
If you don't, they'll kill you.
不走，下一个就是娘娘
Abe,
阿部
Yes?
在
You've been here a long time.
你到大唐那么久了
Time to go home.
是你该回家的时候了
But not with me.
我不会随你去的
Abe!
阿部
M'Lady
娘娘
You had something else to say to me?
上次在沉香亭要告诉我的话，你不说了吗
Towards the end of the feast
在极乐之宴的最后一刻
Lady Yang foresaw her fate.
贵妃似乎已经预感到了自己日后的命运
She'd been the glory of the dynasty.
强盛时，她是帝国的象征
In crisis, it no longer needed her.
危难时，大唐将不再需要她
At Maweiyi,
在马嵬驿
she craved all words of love.
她因此渴望拥抱所有的爱
She knew
她知道
as death approached
死亡来临时
they could be...the last.
她再也听不到，爱的表白了
I understand.
我懂了
It's all in your eyes.
你的眼睛都告诉我了
I'm content.
我很满足
The rebels had killed her family.
叛军已经杀了杨家兄妹
If they took her too, or she killed herself,
如果再交出杨玉环，或者杨玉环自杀
the helpless emperor
失去皇帝权威的李隆基
would be doomed as well.
自己只能是死路一条
If she went to Japan, the rebels
如果她随阿部离开，叛军一旦察觉
would've killed him.
皇帝本人还是死路一条
For the sake of his dignity and safety
所以，为了皇帝的颜面和安全
she could neither live nor die.
杨玉环的生死两条路，都被堵死了
You're saying there's a third way?
难道除了生死，还有另外一条路吗
I have an foolproof plan
我有一条万全之计
to save the emperor- and M'Lady too.
可保皇上平安，也可保娘娘不死
Red Crane, lie down.
丹龙，躺下
I call this the "lmm0rtal Path".
这是一条脱身之计，名叫尸解大法
It resembles hibernation.
就像万物冬眠一样
I can put M'Lady into a deep sleep.
只要一根针，我就能让娘娘长眠
One needle
一针刺入
stops the pulse, breath
娘娘的呼吸脉搏就会停止
and heartbeat.
心跳也没有了
It fools the gods themselves.
神鬼来验，也是一具尸体
Hence- the "lmmortal Path"!
所以叫尸解大法
Then what?
以后怎样
Though she won't be breathing,
施法之后虽然没了气息
she'll come to no harm.
但娘娘不仅毫发无损
Neither will she age.
还能容颜不老
We seal her Qi inside her body.
这都是因为封闭了真气的缘故
I won't let him do this to you.
玉环，我绝不会让黄鹤对你这么做
Your Majesty
皇上
look!
请看
You're awake?
你醒了
Sit up.
起来吧
The Qi isn't yet in full flow.
这不过是气脉初通的症象
He just needs a short rest.
歇会儿就好了
It's the only way to save her.
皇上，这可是娘娘唯一的活路啊
Say you put her into a deep sleep.
你不是说，可以让娘娘长眠吗
What next?
事后怎么办吶
Seal and bury the coffin.
封棺下葬
Wait till things settle.
待局势安定后
Open it, extract the needle
开棺取针
and welcome her back!
迎回娘娘
Will she suffer?
没有痛苦吗
There's no pain.
没有痛苦
My love
玉环
I'd rather see Eunuch Gao
我很想把我的头颅放在那个盘子上
take my head on a platter
让高力士端出去
than break my vows to you.
可那样就违背了我和你白头偕老的誓言
I won't let you bury her alive!
不许你们活埋贵妃
My love,will you do it?
玉环，你愿意吗
He was going to bury her alive.
尸解大法就是活埋
Yellow Crane put the needle in.
黄鹤的针刺入不久
Soon she stopped breathing
贵妃的呼吸，脉搏果然都停止了
and seemed to be dead.
就像死去了一样
What will you tell Captain Chen?
陈玄礼来了，你想怎么交代贵妃的死因
I gave him the white execution scarf.
已经交代嬷嬷缝好了白绫
But she has no bruises on her neck.
那得有人在贵妃的脖子上做出勒痕
Chen won't fall for it.
陈玄礼他看了，才会相信
Eunuch Gao, you do it.
高力士，你来做
So... I'll be punished for her murder?
你想让我背负杀死贵妃的罪名
And you did it behind His Majesty's back.
而且没有告诉皇上，你就杀了贵妃
I did it for you, Your Majesty-
我勒死娘娘，是为了皇上啊
I did it for you.
我是为了皇上
The emperor convinced Captain Chen
皇帝终于让陈玄礼相信
that Lady Yang was dead.
杨玉环已死
He was the real master of illusion!
他才是真正的幻术大师
I said nothing.
而我却一直沉默
You're saying-
你的意思是
they never planned to revive her.
根本没有开棺取针的可能
They tricked her into agreeing?
尸解大法只是拿来哄骗杨玉环的一种死法
What other kind of death
还有哪种死法
would leave her so peaceful-
能让杨玉环像睡着了一样
with a heart full of love and hope?
怀着对他的爱和重逢的希望去死
Long live Emperor Li and Lady Yang!
皇帝万岁，娘娘万岁
She was buried in an ancient tomb.
皇帝决定，将贵妃埋葬在古人的墓穴中
All who knew about it would be killed.
所有知情的人，事后都被处死了
I was no exception.
我也逃脱不了
Only the cat would keep her company.
陪伴贵妃的只有皇帝的那只御猫
If you are reading my diary
如果有人能够看到我的日记
remember-
记住
to get to the tomb
要穿过一片水中树林
cross the drowned forest.
才能找到墓穴的入口
In her last moments
到最后一刻
she still didn't know the truth-
杨玉环并不知道尸解大法是个骗局
right?
对吗
She knew.
她知道
She saw his dilemma.
面对玄宗的困境
She sacrificed herself to help him.
她决定帮他一起完成这个骗局
If she knew that
如果她知道这是个骗局
when they said goodbye-
为什么最后在诀别的时候
why give him a lock of her hair?
她还把那绺头发送给李隆基
Did she still love him?
难道她还爱他吗
Maybe she thought this was love-
也许这才是杨玉环所相信的爱情
to make the ultimate sacrifice.
她做到了别人做不到的
I should burn my poem.
我的诗该烧了
I want to visit her tomb.
我要去杨玉环的墓地
I want to know the truth.
我想知道，杨玉环她到底怎么样了
This is it.
就是这儿
Come in.
进来
Who opened the stone door?
是谁打开了石门
Someone was here first.
之前有人来过
Kukai!
空海
They've moved the lid.
有人动过石棺了
Huh?
啊
The lid is askew.
上下没有对齐
Give me a hand!
来帮我
Push!
推
I don't dare look.
我不敢看
I don't want to look.
我宁愿不看
Letian
乐天
Kukai!
空海
Maybe we were both wrong.
也许我们都错了
Maybe the "lmm0rtal Path" was real.
也许尸解大法是真的
What're you doing?
你要干什么
Give me the candle.
把灯芯给我
Close the lid.
把棺盖合上
You're insane!
你疯了
Close it.
合上
Letian
乐天
Kukai!
空海
What's this?
这是什么
Blood from her fingers.
指尖上的鲜血
She wasn't dead!
她没有死
She tried to escape, but couldn't.
她想推开棺盖，却推不开
That's right.
不错
She woke up inside!
她在封死的棺木里苏醒了
You're White Crane?
你是白龙
And Lady Yang?
贵妃呢
Where is she?
她在哪里
You got it
你猜对了
Kukai
空海
She knew it was a lie.
她知道这是个死亡骗局
But didn't know she'd wake up,
可不知道会在棺木中苏醒
or how long it would take to die.
醒来以后要等多久才会死去
Is this vision you and Red Crane?
你用幻术让我们看到的是，白龙和丹龙吗
On the second night of the mutiny
兵变的第二天夜里
Guards took the emperor away.
金吾卫就护送皇上离开了马嵬驿
Red Crane and I escaped
the slaughter and snuck back
我和丹龙躲开了追杀，偷偷地跑回来
to save Lady Yang.
想要救出娘娘
M'Lady
娘娘
She was still alive?!
贵妃还活着
She's dead.
她死了
Shhh...
嘘
The magic makes her look alive.
尸解大法只能让死人面目如生
It can't bring her back to life.
但不能让她死而复生啊
What do you mean?
你这话什么意思
The master said so.
师父说了
You just have to pull out the needle.
开棺拔针，娘娘就一定能醒过来
He said that to fool her.
开棺拔针，只是拿来欺骗贵妃的
Who'd want to be known as her killer?
没有人愿意背负杀死贵妃的罪名
Not even the emperor!
连皇帝也不愿意
So Dad invented the "Immortal Path".
我爹才想出尸解大法
How do you know?
你怎么知道的
They talked about it at Maweiyi Station.
皇上和我爹一到马嵬驿就在小屋里商量
Yellow Crane!
黄鹤
Talked about what?
商量什么
How to trick Lady Yang!
商量怎么欺骗贵妃
But-
可当时
you stopped breathing.
你确实没有呼吸了呀
You can seal off Qi for two days.
封闭气穴，只能维持一两天
Then the person wakes up.
之后就会自然醒过来
I thought the wine
我以为她喝了那杯酒
would prevent her waking.
就再也醒不过来了
What was the wine?
什么酒
Immortal Path wine.
尸解酒
I prepared it myself.
酒是我备的
Dad added demon worms.
我爹在酒里下了蛊毒
Why didn't you tell me?
你为什么不告诉我
I only found out later.
我也是后来才知道的
You visited the tomb with me.
那你知道了为什么不告诉我
He's my dad! I couldn't betray him
他是我爹，我不能戳穿他，违背他
You still went with me to the tomb.
那你还跟我去墓穴里开棺
What did you hope to see?
你指望看到什么
You're as evil as them.
你是他们的帮凶
Get lost.
你滚吧
White Crane-
白龙
Who do you have in the world
这个世界上除了我
besides me?
你还有谁
I have her.
我还有她
She will wake up!
她会醒过来的
Red Crane never returned?
丹龙再也没回来
White Crane-
白龙
The Lady Yang we knew is dead.
那个问我们是不是白鹤少年的杨玉环
真的已经死了
I'm as upset as you.
我和你一样绝望
How can men be so evil?
人心这么黑暗
I want to end this suffering.
我想找一个不再痛苦的秘密
After that?
后来呢
What happened?
发生了什么事
You needed raw meat!
你需要一块生肉
I know.
我知道
I can't die.
我不能死
If I did, she'd have no one!
我死了就没有人陪伴贵妃了
Your spirit entered the cat.
一入猫身
You'll never be human again.
你就永远回不到人身了
Fine with me.
不要也罢
Once inside the body of the cat
我的灵魂和御猫合为一体以后
his memory became mine.
他的记忆成了我的
Suddenly
在冥冥中
I heard Lady Yang's desperate screams.
我听到了贵妃在石棺中绝望的嘶喊
How'd you get back here?
你怎么回来了
Weren't you protecting Lady Yang?
我不是让你守着娘娘吗
I was protecting her!
我是守着她
But I got hungry.
可是我饿了
And no fish eyes to eat there.
山洞里也没有鱼眼睛可吃
But everyone thought
可宫里人人都知道
he went blind weeping for her.
玄宗是因为思念贵妃而哭瞎的双眼
He lied, but he knew the truth.
他骗得了别人，可骗不了自己
You need to write that in your poem.
你现在该知道怎么写长恨歌了吧
Or I'll kill you too.
不然我也可以杀了你
You've already killed so many.
你已经报复了很多人
Many?
多吗
Three generations and I'm not done yet.
仇报三代，我还没有杀够
Your final target is Red Crane.
你想杀的最后一个人，是丹龙
That's right.
不错
And Lady Yang?
杨玉环呢
Where is she?
她在哪里
Is she still alive?
她还活着吗
Tell me. ls she still alive?
告诉我，她还活着吗
She will wake up!
她会醒过来的
How long can you lie to yourself?
你难道还要继续欺骗自己吗
The melon magician?
卖幻术的瓜翁
What does he want?
他来做什么
He invited us to the banquet.
他请我们赴宴
Just you two?
只有你们两个吗
There'll be others.
还有人会来的
That's Li Bo!
李白
Lady Yang might speak to us tonight.
我猜娘娘今晚上会跟我们说话
No way.
不可能
Bet?
赌不赌
Sure.
赌
It's Lady Yang's jade hairpin.
这是娘娘的翠翘
So you're the Flying Cranes.
你们就是白鹤少年
Red Crane-
丹龙
Still playing with magic?
你还玩幻术
I knew it was you who took us back there.
我知道，是你把贵妃带到这儿的
I wanted to relive that time-
我只是想重温一回
the golden era of the Flying Cranes.
白鹤少年在一起的好时光
The Flying Cranes are no more.
白鹤少年早就不在了
Yet Lady Yang is eternal.
贵妃，却永远的贵妃
Is she still alive?
她还活着吗
Kukai!
啊 ！ 空海
I've guarded her for thirty years!
我守了她三十年
No one is to touch her!
谁也不许碰她
I know you hated me for leaving.
我知道你怨恨我离开
But I've been with you all along.
其实我一直都在你身边
See who that is?
你看看那是谁
I laid out your body in a frozen cave,
我把你带出水底，安放在冰之中
waiting for this day to come.
就是为了等待今天
That is all I ever wanted.
我的心愿已了
I have no regrets.
没有遗憾
I haven't inhabited that body for years.
我不是那个身体已经很久了
White Crane-
白龙
Lady Yang would tell you
这也是杨玉环想跟你说的话
she's no longer in her body either.
她不是那个身体也已经很久了
Kill me now if you like.
你现在可以杀我了
I knew she was dead.
我知道她死了
I just couldn't let her go.
我只是一直不舍
I'm going back to Japan.
我要回倭国了
Oh.
噢
What about the Tantric teachings?
那你的无上密怎么办
I found in the story of Lady Yang
我在杨玉环的生死里找到的
the greatest teachings of all.
就是无上密
It's in 'Song of Everlasting Sorrow' too.
无上密也在我的长恨歌里
Oh.
噢
It's finished?
诗改好了
I'm not changing a word!
一字不改
You wanted it to tell the true story.
你不是一直害怕它是假的吗
The emotions are true.
可情是真的
White Crane showed us that.
白龙已经证明了
But he's not in your poem.
你的诗里并没有白龙
He wrote it, not me.
诗是白龙写的，不是我白居易
That's how it is.
就这样
I'm off.
走了
For that alone
凭这一点
you surpass Li Bo!
你就超过了李白
I would try the temple a second time.
我决定，再闯青龙寺的山门
To my surprise, the doors opened.
没想到这一次，大门却为我打开了
Master Huiguo is waiting for you!
惠果大师在楼上等你
He says you know him.
他说你认识他
Kukafl?
是空海吗
Red Crane,
丹龙
we meet again.
我们又见面了
Did you find the secret key
不再痛苦的秘密
to bring suffering to an end?
你找到了吗